One of the most important things is make the
reader feel like they're living the experience in the book.
Where does that symbolism come from?
I wrote down the key elements of A Gentleman in
Moscow in a period of about an hour and a half.
Wow.
I plan, design, and outline before I start writing.
I can then reduce the interaction
of the analytical side of my brain,
and that's where you start to get poetic surprises.
I'm very interested in this feedback loop
of you describe something, then you see more,
you see more, and then you describe something.
It's this iterative process, beginning to build in the
layers of the language to suggest a bigger truth.
That's a beautiful answer.
I gotta say, I'm really excited for this conversation
because I feel like more than anyone I've ever interviewed,
the number of things that I have
to learn from you is so big.
And the place I want to start is
with your ability to describe things in detail,
and your vocabulary.
Especially with French words, you know, the
maitre d'air, you know, the au revoir,
like whatever, I'm just making stuff up, but
your French vocabulary in particular is really rich.
Certain aspects of the French language
enter American and English usage over time,
and that you encounter it over time, and
so you absorb it in one way or another.
Certain Italian words, certain German words, certain Spanish
words become a part of the broader vocabulary
around you.
So then you try to make use
of your vocabulary from whatever angle you have.
And I guess a way of thinking about it
too is that, you know, baseball has its own vocabulary.
The city streets have a vocabulary.
Finance has a vocabulary.
There's ethnic vocabularies, Italian-American or
Hispanic-American or what have you.
And so as a writer, you become very
interested, I think, in general in these vocabularies.
And you pick up the words that strike you as
interesting or unusual or what a cool way to put that
or what a surprising, you know, what a perfect word for
that feeling or for that, you know, to designate that person.
So you start to tune your ears
towards picking up interesting language, including technical language,
you know, which becomes fascinating, or biological
language, you know, the language of physics.
And so when you do that, you're going
to be able to make use of it.
And so when you're writing, it's become second nature
to constantly be applying different vocabularies to different purposes
because you think it will
better evoke the situation you're in.
In the case of A Gentleman in Moscow, the main character, Count
Rostov, is an aristocrat born in Europe in the late 19th century.
So it would be very natural for him
to make use of French language in whatever form.
And in fact, all of society in Europe,
you know, is very much in the same direction.
Moscow in 1900 spoke French. None of them spoke Russian.
I mean, they would know how to speak Russian,
but they never would have spoken Russian to each other.
They only spoke French. And so that would
have been true throughout the late 19th century.
So you want to evoke
that. Now, I don't speak French.
But so you then, as I say, you start to draw on every
little bit of French you know and kind of weave it into the language
because it sort of helps bring into sharpness the notion of this
would be a person who knows these things and has the sensibility.
Yeah. Well, what's interesting with that is
that there's an aristocratic tenor in that book.
And one of the things with the aristocracy is there's a
forbiddenness that when I look at societally, if you're not from that,
there's almost a distance that people have.
And I've noticed that it's only in very particular places where
I've really been able to pick up, you know, on that language.
Sometimes I'll go to the Met or when I'm
in Paris, I can really pick up on that language.
That way of living. But it
just seems like there's some intentionality.
But then you contrast that with, hey, here's a
group of guys on the Lincoln Highway in 1954.
That's a totally different language.
Yes, that's right. And again, so that's where you're the training of
being a young writer is you're listening to those different kinds of voices.
But it's not necessarily the spoken
language that you're principally interested in.
So I'll get very interested in.
And then if I'm writing Lincoln Highway set in 1954, one of the
things that I did in sort of I'm not a research driven guy,
but one of the things I did for in advance of writing that book is I went and
read three novels that had all been written around 1954 that were all set in about that time.
So Flannery O'Connor's first collection of short
stories, A Good Man is Hard to Find.
I read James Baldwin's The Greatest Man in the World.
I read James Baldwin's first novel,
Go Tell It on the Mountain.
I read The Man with a Gray Flannel Suit.
And I read Raymond Chandler's Long Goodbye, which is all.
Now, what's interesting about those four books is that they're all written
within about 12 months of each other and 18 months of each other.
Most of them are kind
of set right at that time.
But Go Tell It on the Mountain is,
you know, a young black writer writing about Harlem.
And then Go Tell It on the Mountain is
a young black writer writing about his father's work.
He's towards the end of his career.
And he's writing a noir set in Los Angeles at the
time, having written about crime in Los Angeles for 30 years.
Men with a Gray Flannel Suit is about the first generation of
veterans that came back from the Second World War and became businessmen wearing.
And that's why it's called that, because it was the guys
who rode the train from Connecticut into the city every day,
dressed identically, you know, to go and work
in Madison Avenue and return home for a martini.
And while their wife was taking care of the kids.
And then the second generation was he really depicted that for
the first time, kind of in the development of American culture.
And then Flannery O'Connor is
writing Gothic Tales in the South.
Now, so in this 18 month period, these are four
different American classics which have a totally different language about them.
They're using a different vocabulary, different semantics.
They're concerned with different things thematically.
But they're all profoundly American.
You know, and that's the nature
of being in the American melting pot.
As a culture.
So as I say, I read all those books in the years before reading Lincoln Highway because it's
sort of a way of triggering for me a reminder of some of the different sensibilities of that time.
Yeah, you're talking about listening and reading and having an ear for times when
people describe something in a way that you've never heard it described that way before.
I was just reading your essay on Nighthawks
with Hopper and had that exact thing happen.
Where in the bottom of one of your paragraphs, you were talking about how
it describes the mood was melancholy, but it's not a sad kind of melancholy.
And then you use that sentence and then for the rest of the piece you talk about how in
a city the solitude, the melancholy is actually nice because it's placed in the context of New York City.
And my mental thought was, wow, you've just placed a
new emotion in my mind that I didn't know existed.
Yeah.
And when I think about what I strive
to do as a writer, that's what it is.
When I was in writing education, you know, learning in school and whatnot, I always
thought about impressive writing as big words or trying to sound loquacious or this elegant prose.
But actually, what I really value is that descriptiveness and
that novelty through specificity and a vibrance in the language.
And I read that sentence and
I was like, that's what that was.
As a writer.
You keep returning to this idea of description and it's
certainly a critical aspect in the broader challenge of writing fiction.
But one of the most important things is to make the reader feel like they're living the experience in the book
to some degree, that they feel present and as a result become interested in the characters and connected to the characters.
They can see things unfolding.
Their ideas, their thought processes and feelings.
And feelings are sort of turned
on by what they're reading about.
Now, all that really depends upon making
the reader feel present in the moment.
And so one of the most valuable tools to achieving that in effective writing is through description that is sharp enough
and concise enough that the reader can see where they are, know where they are, not get bogged down in it.
And then begin to sort of themselves move
throughout the room and listen to how things unfold.
So in the case of A Gentleman in Moscow, I know that book is
going to take place, you know, whatever, it's almost 30 years inside the hotel.
The reader rarely leaves the hotel.
So I know it's extremely important when I was writing that, that to lay out the
geography of the hotel early, to give people a vivid sense of the key rooms early.
Because once I've done that, then as events unfold, the
reader will have a sense of the key rooms early.
And so I think that's a really important thing.
And I think that's what I'm trying to do.
I think that's what I'm trying to do.
in that way thatال
there has to be that balance between each activity.
There has to be the balance between
A Gentleman in the keine asks himself
how we do that.
Whe,it's a great access to all.
How we do it is and then take that
in the idea that it makes the reader feelAL existeO
do we need to make sure that
everyone has a desk or something like that?
spare that it could be anywhere, but nor can
it be so specific that I feel like I'm being
bogged down in cold, cumbersome descriptions of the space.
So you do have to kind of, as
you're working through the writing of that description, adding
details, taking details away, is narrow in
on the few elements that will really help
bring that space vividly to life for the reader.
And how do you think about that pacing?
What I've found when I've done video editing in
the past is that my perception of the speed
that a video needs to be at is very different
in my 50th run through the video as a consumer's
perception of where it needs to be
in their first run through the video.
And over and over, people would say
to me, your videos are too fast.
Your videos are too fast.
How do you manage, when you're trying to have
that felt sense of the pacing of a novel,
how do you manage that
pacing when you're so in it?
And so familiar with it?
Yeah.
I mean, that is a whole art form
in itself, because really what you're asking about is
editing.
And so writing and editing are
too closely interlinked, but different skill sets.
And the editing process is the ability to
go back and take a look at something you've
already written and try to
hear it a little bit differently.
And read it as if it's for the first time
to gain a sense of, is this slow for me?
Like, do I find this section boring?
That's never a good sign.
Never a good sign.
Right, because if I find it boring on
the third read, then the reader's definitely going
to run the risk of finding it boring.
So you do have to kind of train yourself
to constantly looking at it a little more coldly
and find what that right tempo is.
I mean, you talk about pace or tempo, the
same idea is, do I feel as the reader compelled
to move on?
Now, I don't want to associate
what I just said with a page.
Right.
That's what I'm saying.
And it's not a page turner, which is its
own art form and there's parts of a book that
can be page turnish.
But a page turner in the classical sense
is really something where really driven by the
action.
So Lee Childs writes page turners and turners
in his Jack Reacher novels, where you're constantly
want to know what happens next because there's a
new crisis or a new danger, or we want to
beat up the next guy or whatever it is.
And that's a certain kind of
urgency that can exist in writing.
in writing, but as a novelist writing in
a literary style, that's not the one you're
looking at. So what you need to be creating is
a sense of urgency for the reader, which may be
without any action at all, right? It may be
that you're drawing the reader in who gets interested
in the psychology of the character, and so they
want to understand what are they feeling and what
are they going to do next, but even though there's
no action involved, you know? Or how is the writer
going to put this next, you know,
because the phrasing of the sentence is compelling.
So there's all kinds of ways that you're trying
to make sure that the writing is drawing the reader
forward, but that may include a willingness
to have parts which are slow. Right, right.
Tactically, as you're trying to work on the
descriptiveness of a sentence or of a paragraph,
how does that happen? Is it the kind of thing
where you sort of live in it and you're just
trying to make it better, make it better, make
it better, or do you find that stepping away from
it is a little bit more difficult? I think
that's a good question. I think that's a good question.
I think that's a good question. I think that's
a good question. I think that's a good question.
For maybe a few months, you come back
to it, you're like, that's off, that's off,
and it instantly comes to mind. All right, well,
let's take a step back. So what I do is
my novels have always begun with a very simple
premise. They have like a sentence where I'm like,
oh yeah, okay, a guy lives in a hotel for
a long period of time. That's interesting. And if that
idea kind of grabs hold of me, I'll start to think
it out a little bit. And usually, like when I had
that notion, which led to A Gentleman in Moscow, within
the first couple of hours, I know a lot of
people have thought about it. So I started with a
guy gets trapped in a hotel for a long period of
time. And then right away, I was like, oh, it
could be set in Russia, he could be an aristocrat,
he could be sentenced to house arrest in a
luxury hotel across the street from the Kremlin. You know,
it could span from the revolution to the Cold War.
So I knew all that very quickly, like in a matter
of minutes.
Where were you when you had that epiphany?
I was in Geneva. And I was in Geneva in a
hotel. And that's why I had the epiphany, because I was
in a hotel and recognized a guy
in the lobby from the year before.
In the hotel room upstairs, I wrote down the key
elements of A Gentleman in Moscow in a period of
about an hour and a half. In the course of
the next three days, I wrote the scaffolding for almost all
of the key events of the novel. But then what
happens is that if it really grabs me, as it did
in that case, I'll start to fill notebooks.
And the notebooks, I'll be asking myself, you know,
okay, there's going to be this section of scene
where the Count's going to meet a young girl,
and that's going to be his first friend.
She's kind of in the hotel, too. It's going
to be in the restaurant. And okay, so, you know,
what's going to prompt the meeting? What are they
actually going to talk about in this first meeting?
And so in my spare time, I'm just—I'm dwelling on
that. And I used to do it while I was walking
to work, let's say. You know, I'd be like,
oh yeah, okay, what's going to happen in that scene?
And I start to visualize it in greater and greater
detail. I can see the restaurant. I can see the
girl. I can see them dining. I can
see their interaction. So the humorous elements of it.
I then can start to hear the story. I can see
the story. And then I can start to hear the story.
the conversation, so to imagine that in greater detail.
I see the food coming, I see the waiter,
all these various elements. And then in notebook, I'll
start to write that scene and write it out
by hand. Now, I don't necessarily, when
I'm doing these notebooks, work chronologically from
chapter one to the end of the chapter. It's
kind of whatever grabs my, whatever I want to think
about that day. But I now know that there's
all these various elements that are going to have to
be investigated. And I will do that for a couple
of years. So at the end of a couple of years,
I'll have a couple of notebooks filled
with handwritten descriptions of what happens in the
book. And only when I know everything that's going to
happen in the book and I can visualize it all,
do I then start writing chapter one. Now, and then
I'll write the book over a year and a half
or something like that. And then I go back
to the beginning and start to revise it from beginning
to end. And I'll do that, you know, two or
three times. So I lay all this out because it's
interesting. And then I'll do that, you know, two
or three times. And then I'll do that, you know,
two or three times. And then I'll do that, you know,
important to inform my answer to your question
or to inform your question, which is that
I don't walk, I don't sit there with a blank
page and not without a sense of where I'm going
and start to try to investigate it as I
go, right? Is I am sitting down saying, okay,
the chapter is, you know, it's the seventh chapter.
This is where they are. This is what I
know exactly where it's set, what it looks
like, who's there, what their backgrounds are, what
I know all that. And so then when I'm writing
the chapter, it's, I don't have to solve for those
kinds of things. Instead, it's really a question of
what are the best ways to bring this to life
in the language? And what's the best way to
craft the poetry of this? Now, I'll point out here,
and I kind of implied this a second ago,
but I'm, as I made clear, I'm an outliner. That's
what I am. I plan, design, and outline before
I start writing. That can sound like it's very,
that can sound very left
brain, meaning very analytical, very,
very precise, very organized. The reason that I do
that, though, is in order to free up the right
side of my brain when I'm in the
writing process. The right side being the more subconscious,
more dream-oriented, more poetic side of the brain.
If I have not figured out all these details,
what does the room look like? Who's there?
What's their background? What happens? If I haven't
figured out that, when I'm writing, that's the part
of my brain that has to be in full action.
Figuring out problems.
Problem solving, all these little elements of the
story. And it puts pressure on or dampens
the poetic side of the consciousness. So the more
I know, the more I can then reduce the interaction
of the analytical side of my brain and free up
the poetic side to take over. And then that's where
you start to get the poetic surprises
of unanticipated ways of putting something or
actually, you know, he's going to look not at
this, he's going to look at that. Or she's not
going to say this, she's going
to say that. You start to,
go with your instincts and you start to
build out something which is both fits the story,
it's completing what you need to in the support in
the story, but it's also a more poetic and lively,
somehow artistically true version of that event
in, as you're drafting it. Then the redrafting
process is you keep cleaning that to
make it sharper and sharper and sharper.
Yeah, that's a beautiful answer. That's
a beautiful answer. One of the, so,
they've 160 points on the page, if
I don't doğru hatırstem shower轉yect into a
roof, or what do you call it. You know what
I mean? If you get a goal off, of course,
yeah, that's a good one. And like
what you ended up with these AfghanOUGH class,
I think it's like theUB's you're
like, he was looking at the reflection
looking at Egypt and you're looking at
this concept. So he was really testing now,
into the optics of life from much
priorso worth to really start by the analysis,
and right after ergreb need, Rafi'i no longer matter.
that symbolism come from in a sentence like that?
Something like that is very often, if you look at
A Gentleman in Moscow as an example, that book
is written in the third person. However, it is not
written in the third person omniscient voice. So
the third person omniscient voice that would be
used by Dickens or Tolstoy, Henry James, that's
a narrator who knows all. They know what's happened
to all the characters in the past, they
know what's gonna happen in the future, they know
their inner lives, and is telling you from
high above, these are the course of events.
So that book is written in a third person,
but one which is not omniscient, it's really more of
a third person which is closely attached to the
inner consciousness of the Count. So it is really,
the narrator mostly tells you what the Count would see,
and tells it in a way that is consistent with
how the Count would feel about it, and follows
his foibles, and makes his mistakes, has his sense of
humor.
You know, all these kinds of things. That's all
built into the narration. So the reason I lay that
out for you is that a lot of the times
when you have a detail like that, that's something that's
coming out of bringing that voice to life.
So meaning that I've begun to understand the Count,
understand how he thinks, understand sort of what
he would care about. I understand sort of
the comic aspects of the way that he would describe
things. So that's less of a question of, how would you
describe the coffee arriving in the morning, and more
of a thing of saying, what would the Count
notice? And the Count would say, oh, you know,
there you go. You know, as you say, the waiter,
he clearly ran up the stairs because he
would care about how hot the coffee was,
you know, as someone, because he's constantly
talking about things like that, about cuisine,
and he's used to being served promptly, you know,
in his life as an aristocrat. That's the kind of
thing an aristocrat would care about, right? Because they
don't have to care about going to work, right?
But he also, he has a certain enthusiasm in
his personality for things like that, and he has
great respect for others who do things well. And so
all that gets kind of bound into that. You're like,
oh yeah, this is perfect. He'll say, you know,
he'll be really focused on the tempers of the
coffee, you know, because that's what suits his
personality. So as I say, sometimes I wouldn't
have thought to write that passage or describe
it in that way. It's really grown out of
putting myself in the place of that character.
And I would say more broadly than that,
that is true of most of, I don't know, at least
90 percent of the passages in any of my work which
readers will come to me and say, this was very
moving to me, this passage, or this was the most
beautiful passage, I wrote it out, or this was so
insightful, you know, that I sent it to my daughter,
or I read it to my husband, or whatever it is.
90 percent of the time when someone comes to me and
says this about a passage, I'm like, oh, that's
a great passage. I'm like, oh, that's a great passage.
It is something which I would never have said in
the course of my own life. It wouldn't have occurred
to me. I wouldn't say it to my children. I
wouldn't mention it to a friend. What's happened is that I
have imagined for a moment that I am this person
who I am not, who has a different background and
has a different personality. I have then put that
person in a situation in which I've never been.
And while in that moment, that person
with that background, that personality, looks around and
says, you know, the thing about it is, you know,
I'm not going to write that. I'm not going to write
that. That is da-da-da-da-da-da. And usually that
comes really fast. And so, you know, like,
oh, yeah, bam. And when I'm done, I
usually am like, well done, Count. You nailed that.
Because that's what it feels like. It feels
like I've heard it from this personality in this
experience, you know. And that's, of course, that's
one of the ideal states to achieve in
narrative writing, you know, which the modern parlance
is flow or whatever, but where you get
deep enough into it that it is happening. And
that's what I'm trying to do. And that's what I'm
hoping for.
You're watching it happen.
I got to ask, what do you make of this
idea of the crazy artist? The person who can't function
and is just horrible to other people around them?
You are a well-adjusted guy. You worked in the
finance industry for 21 years. You went to Yale.
You've done well in a lot of different places.
You're now talking about your writing
process. You're very structured. You're organized. You're
systematic. You're disciplined. You showed up on
time today. You're well-dressed, all these sorts
of things. What do you make of that trope?
Yeah, it's a great question.
Where does that come from? And if it's
a trope that has some truth to it,
how have you been able to avoid and resist that?
I don't remember. There is a very clear
history around that which others have written about. And
I don't remember where it began, but I think
it might have been with the romanticists or the
romantic tradition. But this sort of notion of
the struggling artist kind of became this popular
concept in Europe. And then once
that sort of, you know, the romantic
poets writing about broken hearts and about
loneliness and about sort of these tragic turns
of events and sort of the suffering artist was sort
of bound up in that. And then there was sort
of a series of figures in history that kind
of magnified that, like Van Gogh, you know, where,
oh yeah, he cut off his own ear out of
love and then, you know, killed himself, like, oh my God.
You know, and so that's what it takes to
make a painting like Van Gogh's. And of course,
like any of these kinds of tropes, as you say,
you could have done a scientific assessment of all
the great painters of that time. And you would
have found a much more broader distribution of
the reality of their lives, right? You know,
Matisse and Picasso weren't like, you
know, neither were, you know, suicide committers,
you know. They lived very well, you know.
Picasso was with a new woman every few years.
You know, there's always these things. He
was a difficult guy to be with.
Right. But he led a very rich and enjoyable life.
Sure. So I think that there's
different versions of all of these. There's all
kinds of personalities that are feeding into all
of the arts, whether it's written or the musical,
the arts, the graphic arts. There are people who
are less extreme and less volatile. I think, you
know, it's also, you know, when you're younger as
an artist, it's sort of attractive to imagine,
that's an attractive version of the arts, you
know, is to be sort of fighting against. Like, you
know, you have to know where you are, you have to
common behavior and fighting against
what are the expectations of you,
fighting against social mores and being
alone in the attic or the garret,
you know, like in La Boheme.
You know, that makes it all the better, you know.
But I think for a lot of artists, you
also kind of grow out of that a little bit.
You know, you realize, well,
actually, that's not really necessary.
And it's always not necessarily productive.
You know, that kind of tortured version of art
doesn't always get you to get the work done.
If I talk to, you know, I've had the
luxury of getting to know many of my accomplished peers
in the, you know, current writers across the United States.
And more often than not, if you ask them
how they work, the vast majority work in the morning,
you know, and the vast majority punch the clock.
So, you know, they'll say, I am at my desk.
I'm at my desk at fill in the blank.
You're an 8 to 12 guy, right?
Yeah, I'm kind of an 8 to 12 guy.
So when it's 8, 8.30, you know, some are
6, some are 9 or 10, you know, whatever.
But the vast majority, it's the first thing they do.
And they do it at
the same time with little variance.
And because they've learned over decades
that inspiration is what comes to them
when they're at their desk.
Right.
It's not something that you don't wait to become.
You're inspired and then go to your desk.
Because if you do that,
you will never make any progress.
You go and you sit down and you do the
work and eventually fine things will surface out of that.
And then your job is to kind of
weed out, take the fine things and magnify them
and take the sloppy stuff
and set it aside, you know.
But it ultimately is time at the desk.
There's a lot out there, obviously, of go
follow your passion and just work, work, work.
I mean, you worked a job for 20 years.
And then you wrote a novel.
Yeah.
And then you wrote a novel that didn't work.
And then you wrote Rules of
Civility while you're working a full-time job.
That comes out and you're like, OK,
now I will go become a full-time writer.
Would you recommend that path to other novelists?
Or would you tell people, hey,
go for it while you're young.
That's a good time to do it.
I think you've got to do that.
You've got to figure that one out yourself.
OK.
I think as a writer.
I mean, because as you say, I did not
– I've been writing since I was a kid.
And I wrote in college.
I wrote in graduate school.
I had stories published in
the parish review in my 20s.
and at that point I could have said, all
right, I'm going to now commit myself to this craft.
And maybe I should have.
You know, there's no way to know, right?
And if I had done that, I may have written 13 books
by now instead of five, you know, or four, whatever it is.
So, but I ended up going this
other path, which worked out for me.
But there's a lot of people who, if they choose not to follow their art now, they're either miserable or they enter a
career which is not productive for them or doesn't reward them financially or doesn't satisfy them intellectually and makes them miserable as a person.
So, you know, there's a lot
of variables in there, you know.
So it's hard to know which
is the right thing for different people.
But there's plenty of artists that I
know, talented, successful artists who started later.
You know, I just mentioned, you know, Lee Childs.
And obviously he writes very different kinds of work.
But I know Lee because he's writing suspense.
But he didn't start writing at all in any respect
until his late 30s, I think, because he got fired.
He was a television director.
And he got laid off.
And he's like, I got to
find a way to make money.
And, you know, and he went and stumbled
into, he's like, I think I can do this.
But meanwhile, you know, you have someone like
Colson Whitehead who I'm sure started very young.
And was doing it very actively in college.
And the minute he got out, he
was writing, you know, full time probably.
And it was the best he could.
So, you know, there's different routes.
And you have to kind of decide
what works for you as the individual.
Yeah.
You have some experience describing hotel rooms.
And one thing that was coming to mind as you begin to think
about what you would say is that you could almost think of seeing.
As people would think about it, they would say, OK, so
when you're looking, there's like a scale from zero to 100.
And as you begin to maybe
describe things, you can get to 100%.
But I would almost argue that a really good description like
gets you past what your mind could ever do on its own.
And I feel this when I read David Foster Wallace.
Like if my brain, David's Perel's 100,
David Foster Wallace's goes to like 500.
And I even feel it now when I'm on a
boat because I read his cruising out, shipping out essay.
I see things that I would have never seen.
And I'm very interested in this feedback loop of you describe something,
then you see more, you see more, and then you describe something.
Let's say that you're going to write a story
or what have you or a chapter in a book.
And the scene is a young girl is coming downstairs.
It's approaching dinner time.
It's the 1960s, early 1960s.
She walks into the kitchen and the mother's making dinner.
And there's music on the radio.
And if you said, OK, take some French guy or German writer and
say, you don't know, they haven't, they didn't spend any time in America.
We want you to write this story, this scene.
And here's, you know, some life magazines.
And here's, you know, Wikipedia pages about
America in the 1960s and about suburbia.
And, you know, then what happened is you have the risk
that the writer would write a sentence that says something like,
you know, she came down the
stairs and went in the kitchen.
And as her mother took the bird's eye frozen peas from the Frigidaire
and the Beatles played, you know, love, love me do on the radio.
It's just a cliche.
It's just like, well, it's all.
Yeah.
And it's these sort of like, OK, we get it.
Frozen peas, Frigidaire, the Beatles.
It's 1964.
Everything I expected.
Yes.
So you take a step back and say, well, what?
Instead of that, instead of putting in these landmarks
that tell us where we are and what to expect.
Whatever.
As you say, what we already expect.
Ask yourself, what would the girl see?
So let's say, you know, she's seven years
old or something like that, eight years old.
When a seven-year-old or eight-year-old comes into the room in 1964 and
they see their mother making dinner, you know, what would she see?
And I think that, like, for me, if you put yourself in that position, the first thing
that would really stand out is the amazing thing that of what frozen, how frozen peas work,
which is that when you take frozen peas out of the freezer and
you open them up, you can slide the entire brick of peas out.
Like, they come out like a brick, all bound together.
And if this frozen, it was sort of an incredible thing
when we were young that you would see your parent do this.
And then they would break the
brick of peas over the pot.
And, you know, the child would see this.
And then inevitably some of the
peas would go bouncing across the counter.
And, you know, the kid would go and
you'd try a frozen pea at one point.
You know, you'd.
Well, that's.
That's.
About your mother watching you take the frozen pea and
you're like, oh, that's what a frozen pea tastes like.
And some kids would love eating frozen peas.
And there's a very specific texture and, you
know, central experience to eating a frozen pea.
Anyway, my point being that this
is what the child would see.
Right.
So if you're trying to bring this scene to life from the perspective
of the child, you wouldn't mention Frigidaire and Birdseye and, you know, the Beatles.
It would be this other stuff.
Now, we can make this more
interesting in by saying, well, let's say.
And it is.
It is from the girl's perspective.
And this is what she's witnessing.
Let's say that earlier that day, her mother
has discovered that her husband is cheating on her.
And she was doing the laundry and she finds a note in
her husband's pocket or, you know, and realizes that she's being cheated on.
And so the mother is
feeling vulnerable, you know, angry, frightened.
You know, that her husband might leave her
or that the family would be broken up.
Or, alternatively, let's say that on this day, she
has cheated on her husband for the first time.
She goes to take the car to the car wash.
And she ends up in the backseat of the car as
it's going through the thing with the guy from the car wash.
And she's feeling sort of dangerous and sexy and
excited and alive, you know, and all these things.
Now, either way, when the girl walks in the room.
She would not know that this has happened.
Okay.
And maybe years from now, later in the book, she's going to
discover that that was the day that you fill in the blank.
Mom was cheated on her.
Mom cheated.
Whichever one.
So when writing that scene, in addition to the child seeing these little
elements like the frozen peas that bring it to life in this vivid way.
You actually have to write the scene very differently
with different language and a different tempo, a different tone.
Depending upon which of the two things
the mother had done earlier that day.
Okay.
Because although it would not be known to the girl, somehow it would have to be evident in
the behavior of the mother that the girl senses in the room without even knowing that she senses it.
So that as they say, later when you find it out, you
could go back and read that section and say, it was all there.
That's what was going on that night, you know, and
that's why this felt a little off or that whatever.
So as a writer, then you go into this
situation of, as you say, there's this iterative process of.
Of trying to observe accurately, trying to write it carefully, but then beginning to build in the layers of the language,
your word choice and the poetry of the language to suggest a bigger truth, which is not simply what am I witnessing.
But what is the full emotional content of not only the mother, but
of everybody in the household and how is it in there in that space?
And then how is that kind
of suggested by the historical context?
You know that we are middle class
or upper middle class or lower middle class.
And then you go into that space and
you're like, well, I'm not sure what I'm seeing.
I'm not sure what I'm seeing.
I'm not sure.
And then you go into another class that we're
in Ohio versus a suburb of Los Angeles versus Baltimore.
All that has to be in there, too.
You know what I mean?
So through the writing and the rewriting, you try to get as much of that right at the beginning by hearing these
elements in advance, by sort of picking the tone and the vocabulary that suits this destination that you're going to bring to life.
But then you through the editing and the re-editing, you refine that and make
sure that you're getting it closer and closer to where you want it to be.
I'll add something here, which is that the way I think about it for myself, and I think that all writers approach these things
very differently, but the way I think about it for myself is that I write the first draft for me and for me alone.
So in the writing of it, I'm like, whatever I want to imagine, whatever whims I have,
whatever tickles my fancy, however deep I get into the fascination, whatever I think is hilarious, whatever.
I can go on at length,
as I am doing right now.
I just let it all, whatever happens, happens.
I don't regulate it in any way.
But then once the first draft is there and in
reasonably good shape, I then kind of turn the lens around.
And I say, OK, having written this for myself, full of
vanities and digressions and investigations and asides and diversions and everything.
Now I want to.
I think about it not from
my perspective, but from a reader's perspective.
And this is not about,
you know, trying to sell books.
It's that looking at it from the reader's perspective is a way
of saying, well, I'm going to complete the fulfill the covenant here.
Do my half of the covenant.
When a reader buys my book,
that means they're going to spend money.
And then more importantly, they're going
to spend time consuming the book.
And so that is an
investment by them into my art.
And so.
I owe it to them.
I have certain things that I
owe them in exchange for that.
And one of the things I owe them is to ensure that I've taken that initial draft and I've weeded out the redundancies, the things that are cliche, the
things that are boring, the things that have that are only there because they satisfy my whim, but actually don't play a role in the story as a whole.
So the re the editing part for me, a large portion
of that is taking things out, being getting it leaner and leaner.
So that is really is around the.
The pure economy of the elements that belong in
this story and in the language that serves this story.
And then everything else gets pushed out to the side.
You know, how much of what you
just said, do you feel can be taught?
One of the things that I very much observed was as you were talking about the peas, you
spoke about your experience with the peas and you had a deep sense of trust and conviction about your
experience.
With the peas that your experience would be valid, real enough that you could trust that
and put it in your story and that your own personal experience would be part of that.
And I would imagine that there's probably a
permission that a young writer needs to feel around.
Maybe people are.
They don't feel that their experience
is worth writing about or something.
But out of what you said, if you're teaching a class at
Yale or something, you're going back and you're going to do spring semester.
A writing class.
How much of what you said
do you feel can be taught?
And to the extent that it can or can't be taught, how would you structure that class to help
your students, the people who were in the shoes now that you were in when you were in school?
I am the wrong person to ask this question.
Why is that?
And that is because there are many very talented, accomplished writers, even here
in the city, who do what you say, meaning that, you know, Michael Cunningham.
You know, Paul.
He's a Pulitzer Prize winner of Writing of the Hours.
He does teach at Yale.
Gary Steingart teaches at Columbia.
Jeffrey Eugenides Pulitzer Prize winner teaches it at NYU.
And so and they are great
American novelists who are also teaching.
And so they could tell you I
can't right, because I have not actually taught.
And so, you know, I could I could have
guesses about what's teachable, what's not teachable, you know?
But, you know, for me.
That's a whole.
You know, I really.
the most valuable, you know, practice
is the most important thing, right?
So it's about gaining command of elements of craft.
And teaching can highlight for
you how the elements of craft,
what the elements of craft are,
how they work, how they interact.
Teaching very valuably gives you
a requirement of actually doing work.
Like if I look back in my own
study, because I did take writing classes at Yale,
I did take, you know, I went
to a graduate program in writing at Stanford.
So I was in workshops.
And the most valuable thing that comes out
of those by far is the fact that you
are handing something in.
So it gets you to get things done.
And you begin the process of exposing
yourself to how other people talk about
your work or analyze your
work, which is fine, you know.
But mostly you're learning
elements of craft through repetition.
And if you think of the elements of
craft, and it's a very long list in not
all...
in the...
in the writing of novels, but the
obvious things of like plot, setting, dialogue,
tone of voice, perspective, the
more arcane things, whatever, like metaphor,
simile, or illusion, or allegory, you
know, these are all elements of craft.
And so the best way to sort of
gain command of them is by constantly writing
stories where you are making
use of these elements of craft.
Then I would go an added step
for me, which is to say that,
not all writers would agree with me on
this, and not all writers who teach would,
but I'm a believer that young writers
should write from all kinds of different perspectives.
So you take on different
personalities, you write about different places,
you write about different experiences.
You imagine yourself in the position of someone
of a different gender, of a different age,
from a different social class, of
a different race, from a different country.
And you write about some circumstance that they're
in, and that starts to hone for you
the ability not simply to command
an element of craft, like dialogue,
but to do it in a different
way for a different person each time.
You know, that you're writing, during
a setting, you're writing a story about
an 80-year-old woman who was, had,
parents were very wealthy, married well,
but is now relatively, has lower income, living
in a big apartment in the Upper East Side,
you know, or you're writing about, you know, a kid,
you know, from, you know, the East Side of Chicago,
you know, who's in a,
you know, single-parent family or whatever,
and they're going to describe a room that they're in,
they would approach describing
that setting very differently.
So in that sense, there's no, when
you gain command of the craft of setting,
it's not like it's a single thing, where you're
like, oh, this is how you describe a place.
Or a room, or an environment, because
that's going to change every time you change
the personality and the background of the character.
So what becomes valuable as a young person
is constantly shifting the ground under your own feet,
so that you actually get sort of a
meta lesson, which is not how to do setting,
but how do you start to see
the elements within setting that can be re-approached
in different styles to accomplish the evocation of
a different kind of place from a different interior,
and that's mindset.
Right.
Yeah, what's coming to mind for
me is just the malleability of descriptiveness.
We think of things as these things that
are, they're concrete, this is how it is,
it is a physical object, it
can't change, and you're challenging that notion.
You're saying that the same table
by people from all different social classes,
they could look at that table and see different things.
Absolutely.
One person could see a nick in the wood and
say, oh, this wouldn't have been good enough for grandma.
Another person could say, oh, oh
my goodness, and just be flabbergasted
by the sight before their eyes.
I guess exactly.
It could strike a memory for them.
My uncle had a table like that when my parents
would play poker and I was waiting to go to bed,
or it would be like that kind of thing.
As you say, it can trigger any kind of emotion,
of a memory, and it's within the landscape of the room.
Does it clash?
Does it stand out?
Does it make the room?
You're right.
So you're sort of going to train yourself
in the malleability of description, as you say.
And that's what I'm trying to do.
And so going back to the question,
can various of these things be taught?
I suppose, sure.
But most importantly, it's mastering
craft through repetition and through constantly
approaching things in new ways and then gaining
a greater and greater command over what works
and what doesn't.
Now tell me about the flip side
of this, which is how you consume differently.
Because this to me is the fun
part about getting into the game in anything.
Whether it's I played golf at a high
level, learning to paint a bit, learning to write,
is once you start doing the thing,
you start consuming the thing differently because you
start deconstructing what's going on.
And all of a sudden you develop a critical eye.
What do I like?
What don't I like?
What do I think is refined?
What do I think is sloppy?
And all this happens at a very subconscious level.
And I know that you've been in
this writing group for like 20 years.
You're reading over and over again.
Reading group, not a writing group.
Sorry, a reading group.
Thank you.
Is that where that consumption happens?
Are you doing this a lot on your own?
What is...
How do you consume differently?
You certainly hit on an important thing, which
I think the vast majority of serious writers
of fiction would have a similar story
to mine, which is that I began...
I became interested in writing when I began to read.
Those things happen simultaneously, you know, first grade.
And so from that point, what happened
was my first grade teacher, Mrs. Gomm, brought
to the class a well-known juvenile poet from...
New England named David McCord, meaning
he wrote poetry for the young.
And he read his poems to the class.
And then we were given, you know, copies of
his books at the end of class, which he signed.
And you know, we got to bring them home.
And I just remember being
like, this is the coolest thing.
This is it.
You know, I just love this.
I love everything about it.
I loved that he was writing these
poems and the way he used language.
I loved that he was reading them to
the class and how attentive we all were.
I loved going into the book.
I mean, the whole thing.
And that's when I really decided
I want to be a writer.
And so from that moment forward, reading
and writing were things that were happening side
by side, you know, where you'd start to
read and get interested in somebody and get deeper
and deeper into it.
And you'd walk away with new
insights about writing from that investigation.
And so when you start as a kid, you're
reading the Hardy Boys and you're reading Ray Bradbury
and then you're reading, you know,
sci-fi and you're reading Agatha Christie mysteries
and you know, all these kinds of things
and James Bond, Ian Fleming, and you get into
something.
And you kind of take things
away from it, as you're saying.
But then you kind of shift into high
school where you're reading things of greater literary
merit, of more intricate construction, and you are
absorbing it, as you say, with a critical
eye.
How does this work?
Why do I love this so much?
How did that just happen?
Oh my God, that chapter is amazing.
This character is incredible.
This language is so fresh, like surprising.
How this person is putting things is really like amazing.
I always read with a pen.
And so, and then of course, you know,
I studied literature at Yale, I studied literature at
Stanford.
So you know, you're getting to the
point where you're shifting into an active mode.
Not only are you reading with a pen and
figuring out how the whole book is constructed, but
then you're writing about that, you know,
where you're writing essays on, you know,
structure in Hemingway or, you know, whatever,
you know, the poetics of Melville or, you
know, whatever the various topics are
that you're tackling as a student.
And so there's a very thin line.
There's a very thin line between your own
approach to writing and the way in which you
read.
You know, they're influencing each
other in a very profound way.
And you get to the point where
you do see things out of practice.
You start to see things
in the structure of the book.
You see through the book in a way.
And you say, oh, okay, I get how this is
structured and, you know, in what he's doing here, what
she's doing here.
And you learn from that, you know.
I have written a book.
I have written in my notes, what does this mean?
I am not this person, exclamation,
exclamation point, exclamation point, exclamation point,
meaning the context there is that
you share drafts with very good readers.
And I'm like, I am not a very good reader.
So what does that mean?
What it's referring to is that when I write
a book, I don't share the first draft with
anybody until I'm done.
And then I give it to a handful of readers.
And so, and that includes my editor in New York.
I may include my editor in London.
I may include my agent.
But it will include three, you know,
friends who are good readers, you know.
And so they may be writers.
They may be an editor.
They may be a literary agent.
They may have just studied.
They may have a graduate degree in literature.
But they're people who read thoughtfully,
carefully, and who therefore will give me
thoughtful, careful feedback, you know, people
who I trust as a reader.
And that, you know, those are
the people I will turn to.
The group that you mentioned, which
is a separate thing, is 28.5.
I'm not sure.
But I think it's a great thing.
I think it's a great thing.
You know, we've been reading novels
together for a long time now.
I think it's a great thing.
And so, you know, 20 years ago, three
friends and I began a book group, in essence.
And we've been reading novels together for the 20 years.
And we read a novel a month, basically,
and we do projects where we'll take an author
and read, you know, three, five, seven
of that author's works in a row chronologically.
Or we'll read a series of books set in
the same place or written around the same time
by different people or that thematically are interlinked.
But we kind of, you know,
do these projects and do investigations.
And that's what we're doing.
We're doing investigations.
And then you meet to talk about them.
So yes, those are also places where we
will, at length, break down our impressions of the
strengths and weaknesses of a particular approach,
of a narrative voice, of, you know, elements
of style that were surprising to us, that
we admire, that we would love to duplicate
or whatever, all the kinds of stuff.
Who's somebody who comes to mind
that you learned a lot from?
Oh, the whole project has been amazing.
You know, I don't—there were
very few wasted efforts in that.
Partly because you're in control of it.
You read the first two by an
author and you're like, ah, not for us.
Learned a little something, but it's not our thing.
But then some of you are like,
three, four, five, six, because you're gaining confidence
that this is a rewarding
person to read the work of.
And so you kind of—it self-regulates in
that sense, that you're reading work that
is—that rewards you.
Yeah.
I don't know if you're comfortable sharing the
name of an author, but has there been
somebody who you learned a lot from who
was very rewarding, whose work you didn't particularly
like?
Well, first of all, we
almost only—we predominantly read dead authors.
So I would say that 90% of
the authors that we read are deceased.
The reality is that if you think of time
or history or whatever you want to call it, history
is not very good at capturing
all that is great in art.
It is not good at that.
So there are many great
symphonies that have been lost permanently.
There are many great painters that
died unknown and their paintings are gone.
There's novels that have been written
that no one will ever read.
So history is not good at
capturing all that is great in art.
But history is very good
at discarding all that is mediocre.
有話
So and the amount of time that that takes,
it's like something like 50 years.
So over the course of 50 years,
what will happen is a
lot of stuff that was prominent
will be refiltered and refiltered and refiltered,
and you'll end up with a smaller group of things
which have survived that test of time.
And so like if you think about it right now,
if you go back and look
at the bestseller list for 1974,
1973, there's a lot of that
that would have been highly regarded at the time,
which people do not read
anymore for a variety of reasons,
and there's some that has survived.
And that's a very telling distinction.
So in a world where we
have, I'm turning 60 this year,
you have limited amount of time.
We both have, all four of us have active lives.
We wanna make sure that if we're gonna sit down,
we're gonna read carefully, we're gonna meet,
and we're gonna discuss it in detail,
we wanna make sure that the work is rewarding.
And the best way to ensure that
is by drawing from the past.
Amen.
So anyway, so most of them are,
so you know, there's certainly people where you read
and you're like, oh, that's not my style,
but you know, that's very interesting.
Right.
Murakami was not for me, you know,
and there's people who adore Murakami,
and people at the table adored Murakami, you know,
but he wasn't really for me,
and there's things that he was doing that intrigued me,
and certain things that I'm like, oh, that's pretty cool,
but I don't know if it suits me, you know?
Um, and there's things that, you
know, that I think are interesting.
Um, and there's things that,
you know, I think are interesting.
And there's things that, you
know, that I think are interesting.
I'm like, I'm not interested in
what you're doing with that, you know?
So, you know, but at the same time,
you're like, oh, this is a very accomplished writer.
So you're willing to go along for the ride,
and you try to see and
understand what he or she is doing,
you know, from their perspective,
or what they're trying to achieve artistically.
And some people can be quite uneven.
You know, the writers have different approaches to things.
If you look at Don DeLillo,
you know, he's an amazing writer,
you know, and one of the
greatest writers in the world, you know,
and one of the greatest
writers in the world, you know,
one of the great living American writers.
And he is, you know,
he's, you know, he's, you know,
he is near the end of his life.
I don't mean that as a criticism.
I hate to say that about him.
I mean, he's old, right?
But if you looked at his career,
his first three novels were published in three years.
And they're super uneven.
And they're totally unsatisfying in how they end, you know?
And you get this sense that
he's just moving through them really
quickly as he's exploring things that he's doing, you know,
and figuring out what is going to
be the landscape that he operates in
and how is he going to use language
and what are the themes that intrigue him.
And you work your way
towards White Noise and you're like,
oh, that's a masterpiece, you know,
and Underworld even better, you know.
You know, Philip Roth was a
little bit like that for us.
You know, we read Roth's work and his
work just gets stronger and stronger over time.
You have novels who go
in the opposite direction, you know.
I've mentioned a bunch of guys.
I mean, we read women too.
But like Hemingway, I mean, some
of his late work is unreadable.
It's just terrible.
It's amazing he wrote it.
Whereas some of his greatest works,
he's not 30 years old, right?
And so you can have that.
But you can have Roth
where he's, you know, moving along,
writing great books and very highly regarded.
And then suddenly late in life,
he's writing this series of longer,
increasingly long and complex works, you know,
like American Pastoral and things like that.
So within that oeuvre, you know, you're going to have a
lot of things that you're going to be able to do.
And you're going to have a lot of
things that you're going to be able to do.
And within that oeuvre, you may
say, you know, this was uneven.
This I didn't like at all.
But oh my god, over the corpus,
this incredible body of work is being developed.
And then there's a couple of
real masterpieces embedded in here, you know.
And he or she has evolved over that time frame.
How often are you looking at specific sentences?
Like I've seen you talk about Calvino's first sentence.
You are about to begin reading Italo Calvino's new novel.
Like hilarious.
It's hilarious.
It's the greatest first sentence of all time.
It's so self-indulgent.
It's hilarious.
So like when you read something
like that, what pops into your brain?
Yeah, no, we, I mean,
our group will definitely do that.
I mean, we'll talk about themes and
the characters and the bigger things more often.
But we will interrupt.
So someone will say, wait a second, I just want to, you
know, when we're talking about how well the art, the writer writes.
You know, somebody will say it.
And you will all turn to that page and we'll read through the
paragraph or whatever and admire the way that something is constructed, you know.
And I remember in the case of Verdi.
In the case of Roth in particular, there's sections where, and I can't remember which book,
but as an example where in a paragraph it will begin from the perspective of one character.
And then kind of shift into an omniscient version.
And then it will shift into the mindset of the other
character who, you know, you kind of turn around like this.
And without it ever breaking and without there being a disruption, it's just
this very fluid thing which is very unusual, you know, and very skillful.
And you're like, oh, that's nice.
You know.
And so you'll stop.
And sort of dwell over how that was achieved.
And then again, you sort of pack that away and say, yeah, that's an interesting thing to, you know, to draw out at some point
is to think about a shift in don't be married to the, why does it have to be, you know, omniscient third all the way through?
What if all of a
sudden it's from this other perspective?
Or if most of it's from her perspective, why can't I suddenly have
it shift in this scene where we hear it from his perspective, you know?
You got to be careful you do that
because it could be jarring for the reader.
And the reader may be like, what?
You know.
But if you pull it off, it's a great,
you know, as a great element to the storytelling.
Yeah.
How, what's your relationship now with poetry?
You're talking about learning poetry when you were younger.
And what, how does that factor into your work?
Because there is a poetic element for sure.
But you haven't spoken about it yet.
You know, and I'm not, I am not, I
am a reader of poetry, but not a great one.
And I have, you know, I've read
poetry over the course of my life.
I love Whitman.
I love Dickinson.
I love T.S. Eliot.
You know, there's a variety
of poets that I've loved reading.
And you do learn a very different thing from them than you learn from reading
Joseph Conrad or, you know, or Henry James or Edith Wharton or, you know, Toni Morrison.
But within the scope of narrative, there
are writers who tilt to the poetic.
So Toni Morrison actually is an example where some
of her work, the sentences are pushing towards poetry.
And so you're, you don't have to necessarily read
poetry in order to master the, you know, poetic sensibility.
You know, you can find that
in the way that certain novelists write.
And there is, you know, where prose ends and
poetry begins is a very mysterious thing, you know.
And it's also something that you, that I think for me in writing narrative,
you have to kind of dial it in and dial it out, you know.
If you wrote in a pure narrative, you know.
If you wrote in a purely poetic style from beginning to end in the
narrative, it could be very difficult for most readers to get into the material.
Because poetry can be very demanding in terms
of, it can mean four things at once.
And you're kind of like
saying, wait, where is this happening?
And what, is it her?
Is it him?
And is he angry or sad?
Or, you know, you can't
quite tell with poetry, you know.
And that's part of it.
You start to break it down.
Well, if you had that feeling over a long period
in the course of a novel, you would eventually get it.
You would eventually be like, enough.
You know, you, a novel, kind of the deal with a novel is that
there is this invitation to let you get settled so you know where you are.
And then there's the, try not to fool you, but to lure you in to say, okay, now things are going
to get a little bit more out of control or a little bit more poetic or a little bit more dreamlike.
But stick with me, you know.
Because I think when you come out the other side of this passage, you're going to
be like, yeah, that was worth it, even though I don't fully know yet what it means.
But the more I read, I can go back and reflect on that and
say, oh, yeah, you know, that feels, it's in harmony with these other events.
You know what I mean?
So there's this sort of, between the prose and the poetic, you have to, I think, sort of
create a balance and know when to shift and shift back in order to not drive your reader nuts.
Yeah.
And then let's go into something a little
bit more concrete now and talk about manifestos.
I know you like manifestos.
You've read manifestos.
I love the futurist manifestos.
Yeah.
I love the manifesto.
I love the energy and almost
the sheer braggadocious arrogance of a manifesto.
It's like, this is the way it is.
This is how it needs to be.
There's an energy.
Even I can feel it in the way I'm speaking.
It's like this bodily lion-esque roar
that is inside of a manifesto.
What sorts of manifestos have you read?
Well, I mean, I've read, you know,
I kind of collect them in a way.
And so I, but I would not, my description of
them would not be different than the one you just gave.
So I do not need to
elaborate much on what you just said.
And my.
My love of manifestos began, not surprisingly, as a
college student, because manifestos are written for college students.
I mean, for 19 year olds, you know, and that's and that's why revolutions are populated with 19 year olds, you
know, and they also also historically countries where there's a large population of 19 year olds are at risk of revolution.
Yeah.
Because you know nothing.
And then all of a sudden somebody
comes in with some super strong opinion.
And now you're like, I know everything.
This is the way.
It turns on every light.
It stimulates every electrical nerve.
And it's like.
And so.
But.
But artistically, I think what was interesting to me about is reading those first manifestos as a
younger person was, you know, the surrealist manifesto of Breton or or the Communist manifesto is amazing.
Is it's as you say, it's this assurance.
It's the idea of taking
language and tying it towards action.
You know that this is not much.
I just describe something for you.
This isn't a parlor game.
I'm not trying to satisfy you with
some story of a woman having tea.
You know, this is about the world right now.
And you know, and and the way you look at
things and it's wrong, you know, and this is right.
And, you know, and you know, and
you need to look at it that way.
So as you say, this is great sort of urgency.
So the lesson, though, to me is, is you is as a writer is, wow, that's a really interesting energy
to introduce into language, you know, and and the way in which that self-assurance can translate into energy is very interesting.
And you actually could use that in a domestic novel
in different ways at different moments in time to your interest.
You know, but it's it's again, instead of that going back to the way where it began, which
is that you're constantly kind of gathering as a writer, I think different languages that you could use later.
And we talked about technical languages and
and and, you know, lingos and and slangs.
Well, the manifesto is a type of language, you know, and if you look at
all the great artistic manifestos and the political ones, they all have a different language.
They all have a different language.
And they overlap a lot in terms of style.
You know, they're learning from each other and they they so anyway, it's its own
form of what's tactically going on to get that bump, bump, bump, bump, bump, almost that.
How does the writing lead to that crescendo where it comes
in at the end goes like what is actually happening technically?
Well, you have to go scan,
you have to go scan each one.
But you're right. It's very staccato.
Yeah, no, it is.
It's it's it doesn't slow itself down.
It doesn't bog itself down on examples.
It's pushing forward at all times.
The next idea and the
next idea and the next idea.
And it doesn't over elaborate, you know, so there's like seven
declarations, you know, in 14 sentences, whatever that kind of thing.
But but yeah, I know I'm very
fond of that whole category of language.
You have this I think it's
your second most popular tweet ever.
You know what it is?
No, I am.
I am not.
I am not much of a tweeter
and I don't have much of a following.
But go ahead.
You you you show this art nouveau door.
Oh, you're like, I want to write.
That I forget exactly what you said.
It's like you show a door, an art nouveau door.
You're like, I want to put that on paper.
Yeah.
And I have no idea what you mean.
And I also know exactly what
you mean at the same time.
Yeah, I know what you mean.
Yeah.
You know, I think that that the part of the life of a writer is you're constantly listening or looking
or and your mind is is moving on from what you're looking at and what you're hearing to what you're hearing.
Yeah.
And I think that's what
I think you're trying to do.
You're trying to to imagine something beyond it, you know.
So, I mean, I was seeing a
little bit of a tongue in cheek there.
The the this is this art
nouveau door, incredible intricacy, super elaborate.
And so you just imagine, I don't know what's behind
that door, whatever world is going on behind that door.
You know, it's enticing, whatever it is.
Right.
But.
You know, you go to a restaurant and you see two people talking and they
look very different from each other and, you know, they're not it's not a business meeting.
And, you know, and you're like, oh, that's interesting.
You know, what's going on there?
You know, the petite woman of 20 and that
60 year old 300 pound guy in a suit.
Like, what is that?
You know, is that her uncle?
Is that, you know, is that she an intern?
Is, you know, you know, what is is, you know, what
what is that, you know, is going on in that situation?
But but whatever it is like your conversation.
You know, whatever it is like
you're constantly looking at these little things.
You know, I have a collection of short stories which is
coming out in April called Table for Two and a number.
And there's a novella in that collection as well.
But there's six New York stories in there.
And I think almost all of them, maybe five out of six, begin began in real life with
seeing a very small thing and being like, oh, well, you know, I wonder what that's all about.
Or what if you know what if this,
you know, a lot about what if into that.
And a good example is there's a
there's a story there called The Bootlegger.
And it's a guy, a young professional and his wife, you know, in their 30s, sort
of yuppies, end up at Carnegie Hall, very excited their first time they subscribe to Carnegie Hall.
And he's the husband is
a little bit full of himself.
And they sit down and he realizes that the old guy in a
trench coat sitting in the seat next to him is recording the concert.
And it starts to drive him crazy.
And in the way Carnegie Hall works
is that he's sitting in a trench coat.
And if you subscribe to a series, it means that you have the
same seats every time you go to see a particular type of performance.
And whoever sitting next to you is the same person.
So he knows that if he comes back, it's going to
be any he comes back and it's the same guy recording again.
And it totally spoils the concert for him.
And eventually he does something about it.
OK, so and and goes and speaks to security
and all kinds of shit goes, you know, goes wrong.
And both between.
The old guy, the Carnegie Hall, him,
his relationship to his wife, his own feelings.
It all kind of gets, you know, out of me.
Mushrooms out of control is that happened to me.
I mean, I was with my wife in Carnegie Hall.
The guy sitting next to me had the you know, was
was recording the concert and it spoiled the concert for me.
And like all that is in like
the first page of the story, in essence.
But then everything else is what I didn't do.
You know, but but, you know, I just.
I just remember being there in Carnegie Hall fantasizing, you know, as the as the concert was being ruined by my,
you know, awareness of this guy, you know, breaking the law in Carnegie Hall of recording and acting like nothing's happening.
You know, is that it is that I without listening to the
music that I was paying there, hear the music I was fantasizing about.
I'm going to go and tell security and
then this would happen and this would happen.
Right. This would happen, you know.
So so, you know, you have these things.
So it goes back to this.
So it goes back to this, as I say, that the door in a way was sort of a
cheeky metaphorical version of the same sort of thing, which is that you take this little moment that you witness.
You did something you've happened or it's an idea that
comes to you like the guy trapped in a hotel.
And then you kind of go through that door
and you start to imagine what if this happened?
What if this? How about that?
How about that? And, you know, in my own work, I've often thought
about it as particularly for the bigger projects is that I call it.
And I was.
I guess it's not a coincidence.
I call it the opening of doors, which is that if I have an idea for
a story, the way it almost happens as I begin to imagine what the story might be.
It's as if you walked into a mansion or whatever, an elaborate hotel or whatever, a mansion
could be abandoned or it could be, you know, fully ring and all the doors start opening up.
You know where you're like, oh, yeah, there's a
room for that room for this room for that room.
But that's the feeling of when a new idea.
I can tell it's got promise is because
when I'm like, OK, what happens in this story?
And I'm like, oh, this could happen.
This could happen. This could happen.
This could happen. And we're not even finishing
what each any one of those individual ideas are.
They're happy. It's they're
they're firing like synapses unfolding.
It's unfolding. And then you're like, you take a step back and
you say, I don't have to write down any of that necessarily.
It's more what I now know is
that this thing, this thing could be big.
Like it can go in many different directions.
It can incorporate many realities.
You can have many different.
It can have many layers to it.
It can have many kind of individuals and events.
You know, I can feel the richness, you know, through this, as I say, the
feel of the physical feeling of all the doors in the building opening up at once.
You know, how we with this.
What is that hotel on the Upper East Side?
It's I think it's called the Madeline room.
There's the jazz club and it's the hand paint.
It's like French in the Carlisle.
Yes, exactly. The Carlisle Hotel.
So so.
Oh, yeah.
Because it's Madeline is the character.
It's Bemelmans is the bar.
Yes. And Bemelman is the.
Is the artist who did the mural
and who did the children's book Madeline.
There we go.
Thank you.
So a few comments.
So the first thing is
it's interesting when I write nonfiction.
This is that core moment
for so many of my students.
It's when they find not the door, but the core thing that they're saying,
the one line or the one paragraph that then they can orbit everything around.
Once they get that clarity, I
just see an explosion in momentum.
I remember being on a date.
On a date at the Carlisle Hotel and they have the they
have the jazz in there and it's sort of going and bumping.
The drinks are so expensive like I've never seen.
But you were talking about that guy at
Carnegie Hall and I had a very similar moment.
Like if I wrote a short story,
this is the story I would tell.
There was one of the most beautiful women I've
ever seen in my life sitting at the bar.
And she was in this like tight black skirt.
And I was like, what is going on here?
And one of the guys sitting next to
me goes, hey, I think that's just a prostitute.
And I was just like, that's a prostitute?
Like what is going on here?
And my whole sense and sensibility of like what New York was, what was possible in the city, like the levels of
society of being in this room and literally entering a world that I not only had never been in, but didn't know existed.
Yeah, right.
That was one of those doors for me.
Yeah, that's nice.
Yeah.
Who is this woman?
What is this club?
Why is it the hand painted walls?
And that's the door for me.
Yeah.
That's very funny.
You know, it's a funny thing, man.
It's a funny thing.
Let's finish off by just talking about New York.
I think that this is for a sense of place.
You have a line where you talk about New York of being this,
just this city of passions, you know, of you go to many cities.
And they're just LA, sort
of known as an entertainment city.
I live in Austin, Texas, sort of barbecue and technology.
But New York is somehow a hub for everything.
Yeah.
And how does that influence your
writing, show up in your writing?
And your description of what
I said is a good one.
You know, I really began thinking about when I wrote Rules
of Civility, which is set in New York in the 30s.
And that's where in writing
that and thinking about that book.
And about the lives of these characters in the
late 30s, this young woman and Katie in 1938.
It really sort of struck me for the first time that
New York is, we always talk about it as a melting pot.
And what we mean by that is ethnically and as a religious
melting pot, an ethnic melting pot, and a melting pot of nationalities.
But in a way of equal influence in the history of
the city is that it is this melting pot of the passions.
And by which I mean that there are a number,
a large number of people who are in New York.
And they're all from New York.
And there's a large number of professional pursuits where New York City
is the, if not the capital, then one of its key capitals.
And that would be in journalism, in cuisine, in dance, in obviously Broadway
theater and plays and musicals, in architecture, in finance, in the law, in advertising.
Well, New York City is the capital of if
not the, as you say, one of the capital.
as you say, one of the two or three, or
the capital of all those pursuits. And so what that
means is that when you have a place where that
is the capital of an endeavor, it means that young
people every year come to pursue their dream
in that endeavor. The young dancers, the young theater
performers, the young chefs, the young ad execs, the
young people who want to make it on Wall Street,
the young models, whatever, they come. And because
each of those fields draws on a very different
kind of person, it means that if you look out
at sort of the 25 to 30-year-old culture in New York
City, it's people from all these different
walks of life pursuing all these different dreams
simultaneously in the same place, you know, with the
same sort of ultimate hopes. And I think that
adds this incredibly strange texture and a
very exciting texture to New York City. And
so it makes it great fun. And, you know,
Rules of Civility is very much about that. Actually,
that is a case where
we're in the St. Regis Hotel right now, and the
King Cole Bar, which is the bar with the mural in
this hotel, is a key scene in Rules of Civility,
you know, because it has that vibe of what you're
describing at the Carlisle, same kind of vibe in
terms of people, young people there, and it's kind
of tourists, but also, you know, rich locals and
finance guys and all kind of being the model, all
kind of piled in there. And you
sort of get the sense of the electric,
electricity of the city, and that the man, Maxwell
Parish is the muralist behind the bar of Old King
Cole. You know, that's been there for a hundred
years, right? And you think about that, like that,
that the idea that the room just keeps changing,
I mean, the room doesn't change, excuse me, the
people, right? You know, like musical chairs,
you're constantly, decade after decade, have a new
group who's coming in and sitting behind the same bar
and looking at the same mural with the same intentions.
Like that's, you know, amazing.
That's an amazing thing, you know, even to consider. You know, and
Lincoln Highway is, has a portion of itself in New York City.
And it was sort of fun, kind of fun to kind of, begins in
the Midwest, comes through New York, and then, you know, ends up in the Adirondacks.
And as I say, most of the short stories in the new collection are set in New York. So
New York is, it's not the only thing I write about, but it is fun stomping ground, for sure.
Hey, thank you so much for doing this.
My pleasure.
This is fun.
Thanks so much, David. I really appreciate it. Thank you.
Yeah.